foreign
[Applause]
yes is this Denise yes how are you it's
Frankie Freitas oh hello how are you
very good it's really good to talk to
you yeah nice to talk to you I had I had
been thinking about you quite a bit
before I received the your email and I
found that such a coincidence and I
wanted to ask you to come on the show to
talk about the work that you enjoy have
been doing with triple take you know get
a little bit of your history and and
also I'm sure people would be very
interested in hearing about the products
that you create where they're available
and I also understand you create some
dcg plates that are available too that's
right yes uh we make uh we make
yeah and so they basically what we say
is that you get the maximum benefit them
first
in days or so then they start uh dying
off but they're still usable for
two weeks
but after about uh three and a half four
weeks uh you'll still get an image but
it will be a much lower quality the
image will be
and the image green shifts
are they available or as red sensitive
someone called Tom B uh Canada who said
he was going to try them with a dime but
I never heard anything back about that
oh okay so yes you can put a die in them
but after you've sensitized it by just
doing it in the dark yeah but I've never
tried it but the problem is it takes law
the exposure is very very long yeah so
even even with green it's fairly long or
blue uh with the 488 it's not too bad
at these two with these dial lasers it
is very long because you're right at the
bottom of the of the sensitivity so so
with with the red heeny you could go
away for the weekend and come back and
well
you're not that bad
you could certainly go away have lunch
and come back yeah the the the 488
that's hecat isn't it
argon laser he got his uh for 13 I guess
okay you don't see many keycards around
anymore
after for I mean they are at the bottom
of dot matrix machines oh really yeah
yeah I I know Doug Miller used to use
them in Philadelphia there was a place
uh oh geez what was the name of it uh
I'm from forgetting about it was right
down on Delaware Avenue and Douglas
Miller holographic design I know they
did uh dichromated uh work right in the
basement there right down by the river
in Philadelphia and they were using a
heat CAD laser down there yeah yeah
because I mean the the peak of the
sensitivity
UV around about 350. yeah so as you get
more and more into the uh into 400 uh it
you get better and better sensitivity
but you also get increased noise
well you know what you're a real Old
Timer with holography aren't you yeah
I've been here since 1981 I started off
intern with the Richmond holographics I
I did their one week course
uh and then uh Edwina discovered that I
knew a little bit about the physics and
Engineering of lasers and holography so
so she made me a deal that uh if I came
in there and worked with them as a
consultant
have table time in return
she recruited Peter Miller to be their
teacher there uh to teach the holography
course and Peter Miller recruited me
assistant yeah so I I morphed from
becoming a technical consultant to
become a mill as a system and Peter
Miller sort of introduced pseudocalor to
England
so he uh so I was helping him work with
pseudocolor back then in 81 I think that
was 82. very beautiful workout of the
Richmond holographics I'm sorry very
beautiful work oh yeah yeah well I mean
they they had they really got that
pseudical thing down the white
Reflections that they did
are really nice yeah one of my favorite
Holograms of theirs the uh it was a
pulsed piece but it wasn't suited color
it was a lindau man oh yes yes I love
that
yeah that that is a very nice piece so
you you worked for a few other companies
yes you would say that again I'm sorry I
think I overspoken I believe they were
commissioned by this Museum Because the
actual little man was too damn
around to the
so they commissioned Richmond to make a
hologram of it which could be sent
around yeah and you know that that does
that's another application which in
theory seems like a wonderful
application for holography but it's
still something that you don't see
happen quite often with museums no well
the Russian pieces yes that's an
exception yes
and pieces from Ukraine available in the
west back then yeah uh but you're right
you don't see them very often uh I think
partly because it's when color
techniques become better and better I
think that you'll get you see more and
more of them well this this is certainly
in your blood isn't it
boy yeah
it was basically because I started off
as a theoretical physicist and in
theoretical physics choir a lot of
imagination and a lot of imagery and
when I found holography
it was the perfect thing for me because
it requires the imagination but it also
requires that sense of imagery that
sense of being see something
something a glove yeah I don't want to
go off on this part of holography but
I'm sure with your background of
theoretical physics and probably
touching on philosophy as well you're
aware of the writings of folks sort of
such as Krishna murti and some of the
other ones
of course oh really
I was in a class with boom yeah on this
whole concept of the holographic
Universe well you've touched on just
about everything now you you were in
England for a while and then you decided
to come over to the states I guess I
came over uh in 86 without any
particular intent in mind because in
England around then there was there was
no real technical holography there was a
lot of small art studios yeah and I was
working with icon holographics and
carving
and that folded so uh kavi suggested I
come to America because he said there's
a lot more technical work going on here
in America yeah so I basically just got
the next plane out of England and ended
up in
but then I talked to the arkans and they
suggested I try a company called NTS
National Technical Systems yeah and
National Technical Systems had a
contract to make eye protection goggles
for the Army
so I got absorbed into that and I got so
that was my first job here it was
basically uh
Notch felters yeah uh the Arkin Brothers
Bob and
and Bob okay they've been here for
forever they repair lasers and they they
sell secondhand lasers I believe is that
joy in the background
I'm sorry is that joy in the background
yes yes hello hello Joy how are you
for for many many years ago you were not
that far away from me globally speaking
when you were
like home in college right yeah yeah but
she had the same problem I did
uh
when I of course and I asked around and
nobody knew what holography was where
they were
or anything at all about them yeah I
happen to find uh
uh Nancy goglioni completely by accident
and Nancy coglioni then uh told me about
the whole lost gallery and then from the
whole lost Gallery I met the whole
holographic Community but had it not
been for that one accident to meet Nancy
uh I would never have known and joy had
the same problem yeah
yeah I started my studio here in 83. I
had been following holography for a
number of years you know when the museum
opened on Mercer Street in the mid 70s I
guess it was you know
but uh I would just local you know I
mean I never really reached out then I
started a newsletter which I sent out to
a lot of people around the world in the
80s but it was very much a struggle as
I'm sure you're aware oh sure and uh my
the the hours are just you know
incredible you know sometimes finishing
stuff up to three o'clock in the morning
that's even if you have stuff to do
yeah well I mean even
even I I basically started up in my
father's garage building my own sand
table with Fred's book oh yeah and that
was the only way and uh to to learn how
to do it there was nobody around you
could ask anything off no I had I had
three my wife and I are three daughters
so
I had to do everything that would come
down to pie I even did holographic
birthday parties I I would travel to
play other states I could end Delaware
Maryland it didn't make any difference
you know if someone wanted a holographic
birthday party I'd I'd pack up the laser
because you know some people don't want
clowns and things like that they want to
this is when the um
uh when the homeschooling was starting
to Boom you know so they wanted more
educational type of uh birthday parties
for their kids so I'd go down I'd have
laser light little laser light show I'd
lasers Holograms so you have to do
everything you know I mean you're I mean
even today you have to do today
you have to be alone
your own maker yeah uh you're you're a
very very interesting guest because
you've made that leap and and both you
and Joy are out there you know I mean
you're out there this this is what you
know you depend on it's it's not like
you know if if something's not happening
this week with holography you know
you've got your check coming in from the
other job you know and uh well
holography is a very tough
Ness yeah there have been so many people
pulling up on it oh they're people the
the problem is people would spend more
than a million trying to make a million
that's what it is I mean I've been
trying to try to look into why that is
we companies aren't doing well and uh
one of the conclusions I've come to is
that the public does not understand it
uh and so still if you see if you try to
tell them about how
is no way to advertise it yeah and you
can't really you're basically stuck with
making a lot of holograms on your own
time and then showing those around yeah
and when they and when they do cover it
for you so if you get an article in a
newspaper or something a lot of times
they're not explaining holography the
way that it should be in the first place
you know so it's just and they they use
all the metaphors that the wrong
metaphors that you have to have they to
make out as if a Princess Leia thing is
just around the corner yes yeah it is
you mean you mean it isn't
I wish it were yeah
yeah we're still saying 20 years yeah 20
years ago say in 20 years away
that's pretty good I think you're
talking about holographic TV either well
you all have a a whole line of products
that you produce why don't you take a
little a little time to uh I will have a
link to your website for all the whole
talk listeners okay and tell us about
the products that you put together in
each of your responsibilities as far as
getting those products to Market
well the initial idea that we started
off with was that all the holographers
that we talk to all the commercial
business photographers that we talked to
said that the moment you say Holograms
or holographics to a client they would
immediately turn off they would either
think that you were in
uh or that it just was way too expensive
for them
so uh what we thought we would try was
was the idea of producing
a product an object that is an everyday
common Governor Garden product or object
that everyone uses but it would be uh it
would have a hologram on it so that the
Hologram would be an additional feature
to something that you would get anyway
yes so uh we thought things like
coasters clocks uh keychains the common
stuff that I suppose a lot of other
people have done but then we had this
idea of putting it against stained glass
and creating a more decorative product
and so we made a lot of these things and
we've tried to come up with new ideas
like
a little Medallion hanging of a chain on
a metal hook that kind of thing and so
we have a lot of a lot of those around
and then we also thought about logos and
things like that
did not seem to be going too well uh we
put it up on the on the on the website
uh and we try to publicize it but we
also then uh got the requests through
technical Holograms and so now we are
actually getting more and more into
technical Holograms and less and less
into the display stuff
uh unless someone once display
find what you're doing with tech if you
can what you're doing with the technical
what we're doing is basically I'm using
Holograms to create dedicated Optical
setups
if you for example uh want a a an
optical lens or an optical mirror that
only has like a notch filter something
like that
you have company to us and they say I
want this particular Optical function
and so so the two of us sit down try to
figure out how to record a hologram such
that you get that Optical function and
then we make a
we take a photograph we show them the
photograph and we say here is the
Hologram you can see that when you hit
it with white light uh you get rings of
different colors it
maybe something like that and and for
the sake of the listeners what would the
application of such a product be for a
company
uh
well
it's a filter for filtering out
selective wavelengths from a particular
source uh
that's good something like that yeah
yeah
solar collectors uh now you you also
offer workshops that people can come to
your studio and learn holography as well
right well yes we uh Palomar College
approached us uh they have an adult
education section
they approached us and we have had two
three two sets of students so far
taken students
take them right from Theory we spend the
first morning based basically going over
the theory of Photography and then we
spend the
the second half of the first day showing
them just basically making a laser
transmission H1 and we do it all and
they simply watch and then on the second
day it's a two-day course or
day
we make a single beam dentist check in
the morning and we have them set the
Optics under our supervision yes and
they get to take home the uh the single
beam tennis yet and then
one of the second day we set up an H1 H2
system uh to do reflection H1 H2 with
the H1 they made the previous day and
this
time the Optics from
yeah and so they get to take home a
single beam Dennis yet and an image
planed uh reflection and their H1 yeah
what plates are you using now
uh now we're using dcg for these
students
yeah because we don't want the students
exposed to the algon laser it's too
powerful so we use a low power he and
the ngo1 oh I see okay if you find you
find your very good results with those
some very very bright ones
got silver halide
yeah
in an ordinary ordinary light under a
fluorescent bulb without black well what
do you think of the fact that sometimes
regardless of what it is that people are
doing in this field that sometimes
we'll get really good results with
something and other times people can't
do it if their life depended on it or
something in between I mean the
consistency across uh people you know
amateurs hobbyists and I I guess there's
more consistency where professionals are
concerned but as far as you know this
this amateur realm that's that that's
growing by Leaps and Bounds yeah
because I think that partly it's very
very procedural but you have no feedback
from the process yeah so you have to you
have no idea of how well you're doing
until you get to the end of the process
so
so uttering if something happens to be
moving you won't know that until you've
done your shot once you've done your
shot you look at it you have to
basically think backwards of all the
different ways it could have gone wrong
and check every one of them out yeah and
so it's a it's a fairly complicated
process but so long as the equipment is
working and the process is consistent
should get good consist ENT results yes
yeah because there are so many unknowns
it's very difficult to get to that
process I think yeah I think a lot of
the time uh and again I think there's a
lot of misinformation out there there
are
tell you simply simply Point your laser
at the glass put an object behind it
turn on the shutter and you get a
hologram and they don't you have what
Bob has called hobby killers they think
Dave
Ed up on it
yeah with it and if you just carefully
go through uh all your equipment and all
your procedures you should get
consistent Holograms every time
I I find that Holograms will talk to you
if you learn how to listen to them once
they're finished well one of the most
difficult things that I had to do was
trying to troubleshoot a hologram by
looking at the image I mean clearly
clearly dark you know you've done
something wrong but one of the most
difficult things I have to do is if
there's a little ring on the image or if
there's a fading
fading yeah a vignetting
you have to basically
the laser is it my Optics did a did a
baffle get in the way and and that
troubleshooting is a talent all
of it have you ever worked with
stereograms never no that's a demanding
process
you have to do 300 shots and if one
frame goes that's it
yeah so what do you see for the future
for triple take
um I'm I mean I like display holography
I'm hoping that we get a better Market
out of display holography uh but
unfortunately I don't see it as a very
part of of a sales so I see more and
more technical uh work and I think that
uh holography is coming into its own
it's becoming
this strong in the technical
technically called diffractive Optics
now does and this whole field of Dos
especially with Telecommunications
uh is becoming very big
and so I think that more and more we're
going to have to get into that area
micro Optics
micro optic fiber brag ratings
uh the internet when internet 2 comes
out there's going to be a big push for
optical uh interconnects yeah
and uh with uh with these uh wdms which
I which I do holographic
uh there's going to be a big push for
holography in that area I think is there
anything that you'd like to say that I
haven't asked about
ah I can't think of anything offhand uh
I would
I I would promote holography by getting
more and more amateurs involved in it
and and showing it around
I think that the more the public at
large gets to see all the brands the
more accepted it will be
so I'd like to see more Holograms in the
80s there were a large number of public
showings
uh in London and over here and that's
all gone so I'm kind of I'd like to be
able to set up a gallery somewhere in
San Diego uh get holographers to send me
Holograms and make our own Holograms and
have public showings uh so that the
public at large gets to see them more
that would be very nice I used to do
that back in the 80s right and it's it's
very well received sure it is but it
doesn't go anywhere
it's very well received there were
several shows that I had curated uh back
oh I don't know maybe between 85 and 95.
uh
you know this area Southeastern
Pennsylvania New Jersey New York area
very well received one of them that had
people out the door and down the block
waiting to get in to see Holograms
but that's it nothing happens now is
that that could be my fault because I
because I didn't didn't have I don't
think maybe perhaps I don't have the the
experience to take it any further you
know what do you do I mean correct ways
of marketing coming up with good ideas
to do this or do that or business ideas
well I think that one of the problems
that I found in a lot of those
that happened in the 80s was that there
was no follow-through during the show if
you go to an artist Gallery uh you see
the artist's name and you have some way
of contacting the artist somewhere
finding out more about that particular
artwork and I suppose one of the bees in
my opponent is is that if you see a
hologram
from anything from a magazine cover to
let's say a display piece advertising
something you have no concept or idea of
who made that hologram or how it was
made there's no follow through yeah and
so I thought what I would like to do is
if I were to ever do this public showing
thing is to have some way of contacting
other holographers so that when a
holographer sends me a hologram I'll
have a little card giving his or her
contact information some idea of how you
can get to make your own hologram I'm
ready where the shoes are a complete
kind of information package so that you
people who see these Holograms can then
know where to go to find out more to
learn how to do it themselves what the
history of the subject is that kind of
thing yeah yeah and I think that was the
problem then is they came in they saw
the Holograms they said this was great
walked home and didn't fall through and
that was it yeah that was it and well
keep me in mind if you want to hologram
I could certainly send you one if you
ever wanted to put something on display
if you got something together out there
okay thank you yeah I'm I'm still
working my way through that but because
I know that Gallery space is not easy to
come by you've got to go to gallery and
say I'd like to on a grant you have to
sell the concept yes that's true yeah
but yes thank you if and when I ever set
that up I'll contact you
for coming on the show
Joy I'd like to get you on for a
specific show as well to hear about your
background especially uh you're
involvement with women and Optics and
how you know you you had chosen the feel
of physics as part of your uh
part of your education and your field of
work
I was figuring that you were
interviewing him separately because his
background is so different from mine
well we'll we'll get a separate
interview with you up there okay you
know that'd be fun yeah all right
it's a little after three o'clock in the
afternoon here and time to wrap up for
the weekend I have to do the second part
of that holographic stamps that I have
up there that's uh yeah it's a it's a
program that I've worked on with uh Hans
and the history of holographic postage
stamps Phil Italy so that's up there
part one's up there now and I have to
get part two up there and then I have uh
one show after that and I think probably
two weeks from now yours will go up
we're actually in your part of the world
every Christmas so we were saying this
morning that from Christmas we might
sort of
how close are you
in Philadelphia so that's where I go
home every every year for Christmas no
kidding I grew up in Philly yeah yeah I
don't know if you could tell by the
Philly accent Sylvester Stallone Rocky
uh type of thing
learning to speak proper English was
like learning a second language for me
growing up in Philly
yeah well thank thank you both and uh
I don't know if you're on the email list
or not that goes out to people when new
shows go up or not but uh
yeah you can get that at the website or
um I'll actually just uh send you an
email separately
okay there's there's eight years of
programming
this this shows in its eighth year now
and yes
oh that's nice to know yeah yeah so so
you're the ones
all right thank you have a nice weekend
okay bye